Support us and become VIP member
to remove all ads from www.OpenSubtitles.org
A FILM BY PAUL URKIJO ALIJO
Fear the night.
The night. a place rife with blasphemy.
refuge of terrible creatures
that escape the light of God.
The night gathers in
its bosom. perverse demons.
wicked witches. dark tales
which we shall now hear.
In the hour of darkness.
The good Christian sleeps in peace.
With the dawn.
the sun's rays will rise -
light to guide us along
the path of the Lord.
And yet. so they say.
if the night should overtake you. flee -
and don't stray from the path home.
or the darkness will swallow you...
forever.
But who would stray from the path?
Who would abandon the light?
As the saying goes:
"The day belongs to those of the day."
and as the wind whispers:
"The night to those of the night."
THE NIGHT
You... are to blame...
Kattalin.
Why do you keep looking out the window?
- The night will creep into your eyes.
- Can't you hear it?
It's probably a fox.
No. it sounded like a whistle.
I'm hungry.
Tomorrow I'm going to Urdazubi.
To speak to abbot Fray León's
secretary about the orchard.
Luck will finally smile on us.
And Don Mateo?
Has anything been heard of him?
No one has seen the parish priest
since what happened at the church.
It's been a week now.
I hope he keeps what he promised me.
Disgusting.
It needs salt.
Then you cook.
Watch yourself. Katalina.
Show me some respect!
You've embarrassed me enough
before the whole village.
You wouldn't want to end up...
living under a bridge.
Bread.
Aren't you going to eat?
Why won't you speak to me?
You are my wife!
You see?
It has no flavour.
Tomorrow I have to look presentable.
Lay out my Sunday shirt.
I'm going to bed.
I know these past weeks haven't been easy.
But from now on. things will improve.
You'll see.
You're my wife.
No!
Why do you despise me?
Because I'm a cripple?
Look what you've done.
Katta.
Katti.
My shirt!
I need it for tomorrow!
Calm down.
It's all right.
Can you clean it?
Huh?
My belly.
Katta!
Come back here!
Kattalin!
Very well. This first tale
begins with an unfortunate
young woman who entered the forest
when not a single ray of sun remained -
when the road of the Night Above begins.
For he is the night itself -
Gaueko.
Whoever dares enter the night
will be lost -
the darkness will engulf him forever.
For there dwells Gaueko.
lord of those who dwell in the shadows.
His is not a kingdom for men.
What fate awaits those
who dare to enter the night?
The night...
Pello?
Pello. is that you?
The night...
...for those of the night.
The night for those of the night!
The night...
...for those of the night!
Who's there?
Come here.
Hey!
What are you doing here. little brat?
- She was spying on us.
- Reme!
Let her breathe.
Can't you see she's scared?
Graxi. what do we do with her?
The poor thing's lost.
She doesn't look innocent.
Let her speak - then we'll see.
What are you doing here?
- Answer!
- Reme!
Let her talk.
Poor little thing.
Are you alright?
You're Kattalin.
Aren't you?
I've seen you at mass.
What are you doing here?
I left home... and something
followed me here.
It's all right.
You're safe with us.
And why were you out at night?
Problems at home?
I was going to the washhouse with dirty clothes...
and they started chasing me.
It is dangerous to walk through
the forest alone at night.
It's full of vermin.
And your clothes?
I lost them.
I don't believe you!
Kattalin.
you're the one who married
Pello Goienetxea last autumn. aren't you?
Where are you from?
From Landibar.
You're far from home.
And this?
Is it yours?
It's my husband's shirt.
And that stain?
An accident?
Give it to me - I'll clean it.
These stains don't come out easily.
"Outside. a dove; at home. a wolf."
It's no hour to be doing laundry.
And you?
We are Beltra. Remedios.
and I'm Graxiana.
Or Graxi.
We're not here to wash.
We came to pretend we're washing.
This is our time.
- No men.
- No one to bother us.
And no one says anything?
They haven't the slightest idea.
And we'd best make sure no one finds out.
Here we do as we please.
Old by day and young by night.
Things have been ugly lately.
The abbot of Urdazubi
has forbidden gatherings
and the parish priests and
bailiffs are watching us like hawks.
Those inquisitors see witches under every stone.
Just having a drink is enough
to be singled out and dragged away.
You can't trust anyone.
- Here. take it.
- No. thanks.
We pass the time trading village gossip.
And telling ghost stories.
I was just finishing telling
one when you turned up.
You can join us -
as long as you tell one afterwards.
Unless you'd rather go home.
I don't know any.
Surely you know some frightening
tale you can tell us.
Something about spirits -
or witches.
Do you believe in witches?
Reme's a witch.
I don't know.
Careful. girl.
You needn't believe in them -
but you mustn't say they don't exist.
Alright.
My turn.
What I am about to tell you
is no tale.
It happened a month ago
to someone from the village.
To Eugenia. the seamstress's daughter.
Eugenia herself told me.
and now I'll tell you.
Now that it's my turn.
Pay attention - or off you go!
From what they said.
a witch had cast the evil eye on the girl
and invoked an ancient demon.
A dark and twisted being -
born of sin and envy.
An evil spirit: Inguma.
In our villages there is
a belief in the "Etxejaun".
the spirits of our ancestors.
They are owed praise.
for they guard the house
and the fortune of those who dwell within it.
This is how they work.
so long as their descendants
do not trouble them —
and no one. through wicked arts.
disturbs their rest.
Give it to me. son.
Antton...
Don't worry. Maritxu.
You're going to be cured.
Pray with me. son.
I believe in God. Almighty Father.
creator of Heaven and Earth.
And in Jesus Christ. his only son.
our Lord.
who was conceived of the Holy Spirit.
He was incarnated from the Virgin Mary.
He suffered under the power of Pontius Pilate.
He was crucified. died and buried.
Enough!
He descended into hell...
Witchcraft.
Ohpo. dapa. map. map. drepe. Map. ripi.
Propo. tepe. gepe. apa. Mapa. ripi. txupu.
Where are you going?
Eugenia?
I'm staying here.
Don't be long.
Father Mateo.
Katalina.
How is Maritxu?
It is in the hands of God.
Or maybe she's already
in the devil's clutches.
Excuse me.
Eugenia.
Eugenia. how is she?
I don't know.
Antton.
Kattalin.
I'm going to get more wormwood herbal teas.
Your neck...
Kattalin.
Maritxu.
You're going to be fine. okay?
Look.
You're going to be fine.
You'll see.
Yes.
And we will go to the Bayonne pilgrimage.
To dance and jump.
Yes. we will go.
Pater Mateo.
Wasn't she forbidden
from approaching the village?
It was her.
Mother. is she going to be okay?
I don't know. son.
Will Maritxu go to hell?
Don't say that!
But what's wrong with her?
I don't know!
Maritxu.
Maritxu!
You...
You are guilty.
You!
What are you talking about?
Maritxu. it's me.
Harlot!
Get out of my house!
Maritxu. it's me.
Out!
Maritxu.
Maritxu. it's me.
Go away.
Get out of here.
- Maritxu. it's me.
- Out!
- Maritxu!
Why does God punish us in this way?
Can't we do anything?
Antton. go ask old Esther
the herbalist for help.
She knows Maritxu.
She will know what to do.
But don't let anyone
see you talking to her.
Antton. come here.
Poor thing.
A spirit is tormenting
your sister Maritxu. I am certain.
Who was the last
to die in your house?
Grandfather Inguma.
A year ago.
Could he be angry with
your sister for some reason?
No.
Maritxu is a saint.
She's a good person.
Grandfather loved her very much.
How much did he love her?
How much?
More than anything in the world.
It could be him...
This is what you are going to do.
Take this candle and wind it around
the effigy carved in rememberance
of your Grandfather.
Once the candle is lit.
cover it with a bowl.
At first. don't uncover it.
When the time comes. remove the bowl.
Let there be light.
At that moment.
You will catch the spirit of "Etxejaun" off guard.
Pierce a rooster's
heart with pins.
and throws some rotten corn on the ground.
Then recite the following.
Remember it well:
"Inguma. I'm not afraid of you.
Gauargi. light of the night. is with me.
There are stars in the sky.
in the meadow. herbs.
and on the coast. sand.
Until you finish counting these.
do not appear before me."
The window.
Damned wretch!
How could you do this to me?
You are a pig!
Grandfather?
Antton...
Lazy idiot.
You are useless.
You have let your sister
tarnish the family name.
Leave her alone!
Cowardly fool!
Don't you know what he's done?
Anton. the corn!
Anton. say it now!
Inguma. I'm not afraid of you.
Gauargi is with me.
There are stars in the sky.
in the fields.
herbs. and on the coast. sand.
Until you finish counting these.
do not appear before me.
The window!
...28. 29. 30. 31
32. 33. 34.
35. 36. 37...
After Maritxu's death. the priest ruled
that she had been
possessed by a demon.
by a demon drawn by sin
and the evil arts of the witch.
Lord. help my poor daughter.
My God.
I didn't want to...
...but Maritxu was very sick.
So I went to the witch's house...
...and I did what she asked of me.
I didn't know.
And he seemed like a demon.
Maritxu...
That's how it happened.
That's how Eugenia
told me. in tears.
What horrible sin could the little girl
possibly have committed to make
her grandfather hate her like that?
- It's a lie.
- What's a lie?
Maritxu never did anything wrong.
What would you know!
I knew her well.
Maritxu was very sick.
and that witch's remedies
aggravated the illness.
Do you accuse Estertxi of being a witch?
We knew Estertxi well.
She helped the people of
the village in her own way.
Those candle suckers
wanted to get rid of her
and they took her to Urdazubi.
Who told you that it
was Estertxi's fault?
Your husband?
Don Mateo said it.
Estertxi was our friend.
Just like Maritxu was yours.
That vain priest and his
superior. the abbot of Urdazubi.
always turning people against one another.
Let them burn in that hell they preach!
There has been no word
of Mateo for a week.
Since he went crazy at mass.
I know
what really happened to Mateo.
It's my turn.
Pay attention - or off you go!
Mateo was arrogant and hypocritical.
He was obsessed.
Obsessed with authority.
But. above all. with hunting.
He always
whistled like a txistu flute.
He whistled at both his hunting dog
and his parishioners alike.
Hence his nickname:
Mateo Txistu.
Mateo disappeared a week ago.
after the death of Maritxu.
after what happened in the church.
Beloved daughter and sister.
María Oiartzun has left
us in the bloom of her youth.
The weakness of the flesh made her sick.
the enemy that ravages this village.
Nevertheless.
God is merciful.
He loves us.
He holds us in esteem.
Family and neighbours.
let us pray for her soul.
for only thus will she
be spared the fires of hell.
Grant them. Lord. eternal rest.
and may the perpetual
light shine upon them.
In Zion. may they sing your praises.
In Jerusalem. the vow shall
be fulfilled to you.
Hear my prayers.
You. towards whom all mortals go.
Grant them. Lord. eternal rest.
and may the perpetual
light shine upon them.
May she rest in peace.
Amen.
The whole village knew
of his love of hunting.
He used to say that God had
given man the gift of hunting
above all other creatures.
I know it too well -
I kept house for him.
I helped him in the parish.
Mateo was a very reserved man...
...and he confided his obsessions
only to the One he
believed was above him.
I confess to Almighty God
and to you. my brothers.
that I have greatly sinned in thought.
word. deed and omission.
Through my fault.
Through my grievous fault.
Lord. I have sinned.
I have felt in my very flesh.
the tempter devil
trying to lead me astray from Your path.
Hear me. my Lord;
and free me from this burden.
This morning. I went hunting
with my faithful dog.
Why has Your grace willed
that I should stumble
upon the obstinate
blasphemy made flesh?
He said what he saw there had
driven him to the brink of madness.
Search!
Come here!
Search here!
I could spend the whole day dancing.
Give me your hand.
It's more than Pello has ever given me.
That fool doesn't know what he has at home.
I can't stand it. And
the nights are the worst.
You're lucky. With your widowed mother.
You can remain an old maid to help her.
Lucky. yes. but...
"A mere girl. a bald head".
I can't take it anymore.
Well...
...let's get out of here.
To Bayonne.
Let's leave tonight.
Just the two of us.
Are you crazy?
Two women alone out there?
If they catch us.
Pello will beat me senseless.
Then we'll dress up as men.
You take Pello's clothes.
and I'll take my brother's.
If it were that easy...
One of these days. we'll land
ourselves in hot water
...and that'll be the end of it.
I don't know.
He's my husband.
Hello beautiful.
Do you want to marry me?
No.
I'm a little short-sighted.
but I have a fine dowry.
Look.
Come on. darling - give me a kiss on the trout!
- No!
I'd sooner kiss a goat's ass!
Witch!
Come with me!
With you. I'd go anywhere.
Was what I saw real or
was it a trick of the devil?
Should I tell the abbot?
Father Mateo.
Pello Goienetxea.
Sit down.
I have received your request to
work the apple orchard at the abbey.
I have a bad leg. but I
would be a good foreman.
I know the cider-making process
well. I worked for years at Hernani.
I'm sure.
But I called you for something else.
I need you and your wife to
come with me to Urdazubi to
declare before the judge that
Esther Barrenetxea is a witch.
I wouldn't want to get
involved in those matters.
Don't worry.
I know you are a good Christian.
And the Church knows
how to reward its good men.
But I can't say the same about your wife.
I have seen it with my own eyes.
There are three enemies of our soul:
the world. the devil and the flesh.
And. of the three. the most dangerous -
the gravest - is the flesh.
The flesh is weak. but also strong.
Weak to defend
and strong to tempt.
Not even murder is so grave!
For the sin of the
flesh rots the hearts of
good Christians. as it spreads like a
plague. thus condemning.
not only the souls of sinners.
but the very pillars of our society.
Witchcraft and indecency
lead our people to perdition.
More and more women stray
from the path of the Lord
and lose themselves on
the devil's road.
And listen to me.
The only way to
atone for carnal sins...
...is by denouncing a witch.
At the Urdazubi Abbey. we will have the
honourable commissioner
of the Holy Inquisition.
You must go to him
if you suspect that a neighbour
may be linked to witchcraft.
We have already received
several complaints.
Whoever covers up a
witch is also an accomplice.
Damn witch!
It's you. witch!
I know!
I'll follow you to
hell if I have to!
Catch her!
Nobody saw him again.
But it is said that at night.
in the mountains.
some have heard Mateo's whistles
calling to his dog.
The priest is a restless soul
and so he will continue
wandering. cursed.
chasing the hare forever.
That's not true.
How do you know that?
You weren't there.
The priest himself told
me before he disappeared.
Enough pretending.
We know everything!
He swore he would keep it secret
if I gave testimony.
So you admit it - did you freely
sign the statement against Estertxi?
No. I don't...
"No" what?
That they didn't force you?
- Did you do it voluntarily?
- No!
Tell the truth. stupid.
The priest forced you to sign in exchange
for keeping quiet about what happened
between you and Maritxu.
We know everything.
They burned Estertxi because of you.
What?
Imagine how much she must
have suffered when they burned her.
I... I didn't know...
You're guilty - murderess!
No!
You too must
answer to the witches.
What witches?
You are nothing more than crazy old women!
You say we're not? Yes we are.
Look how many we are - a thousand and one.
You will come with us to the witches' sabbath.
IV
THE SABBATH
Pello!
Open!
Please open!
Let me in. for God's sake!
Damn pig.
- You. who wanted to poison me?
- Pello. please!
Admit it!
Did you do it?
Yes.
I did it.
I denounced her. but I didn't want to.
I was afraid.
I regret it!
What was it like?
Did you see Estertxi?
It's not your fault.
We believe you.
But you still carry the guilt.
Akerbeltz must decide.
He knows to whom to give punishment
and to whom reward.
Anoint yourself with this.
Would you rather return to your husband?
Rub into your armpits and your groin.
And repeat with us:
"Above all the thickets.
beneath all the clouds."
Above all the thickets.
Beneath all the clouds!
Beneath all the thickets.
above all the clouds.
Kattalin!
Help!
No!
The horns
of the goat.
The goat has crooked horns.
Crooked are the horns of the goat.
Akerbeltz - the black kiss!
Kattalin...
Whether it be so or not.
put it in the pumpkin
and let it appear later in the square.
But whether it be so or not.
do not believe they exist - and
do not say that they do not.
or they will come to you in
the night and carry you off.
WE WILL MAKE THE MONSTERS
AND THE LIES
YOU CREATED TO SUBDUE US OUR OWN
WE WILL FEED THEM. THEY WILL GROW.
AND WE WILL TURN THEM AGAINST YOU.
DIRECTION AND SCRIPT
PRODUCERS
EXECUTIVE PRODUCER
PHOTOGRAPHY DIRECTION
ASSEMBLY
MUSIC
ART DIRECTION
COSTUME DESIGN
SPECIAL VISUAL EFFECTS
SPECIAL PHYSICAL EFFECTS
MAKEUP. HAIRSTYLE AND
SPECIAL MAKEUP EFFECTS
DIRECT SOUND. SOUND MOUNTING
AND SOUND MIXING
PRODUCTION MANAGEMENT
ASSISTANT DIRECTOR
CASTING DIRECTION
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm